# Jane Hoffswell, Ph.D. jane.hoffswell@gmail.com · https://jhoffswell.github.io · @janehoffswell

#### **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

My research aims to improve how people write, manage, understand, and reuse both code and data through the design of new programming languages and visualization tools. By focusing new languages and tools on the domain-specific details relevant to the user, we can improve how users interact with the system to better promote program understanding, and proactively surface surprising or incorrect results.

### **EDUCATION**

2020 PhD Computer Science and Engineering

SEATTLE, WA Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science & Engineering

University of Washington (UW)

Advisor: Jeffrey Heer

2016 MS COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

SEATTLE, WA Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science & Engineering

University of Washington (UW)

Advisor: Jeffrey Heer

2014 BS COMPUTER SCIENCE

CLAREMONT, CA Harvey Mudd College (HMC)

Advisor: Ben Wiedermann

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2020 - present Lecturer, University of Washington

SEATTLE, WA Taught courses on visualization (CSE442) in the Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science &

Engineering. Developed course curriculums and managed a group of teaching assistants.

2014 - 2020 GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT, UW ALLEN SCHOOL OF COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

Languages and Visualization Tools for Data-Centric End-User Programming of Interactive Visualizations.

Advisor: Jeffrey Heer. Conducted research on the design and development of new systems and program understanding techniques for visualization design. Conducted interviews with

experts to inform research directions and performed user evaluations of the proposed systems.

Summer 2019 RESEARCH INTERN. ADOBE RESEARCH

SEATTLE, WA Techniques for Flexible Responsive Visualization Design

Advisors: Leo Zhicheng Liu and Wilmot Li. Conducted research on the design of responsive

visualizations for news articles, which adapt the visualization to different types of devices.

Summer 2018 RESEARCH INTERN, ADOBE RESEARCH

SEATTLE, WA Interactive Repair of Tables Extracted from PDF Documents on Mobile Devices

Advisor: Leo Zhicheng Liu. Conducted research on the future of dynamic PDF documents,

focusing on the analysis & reuse of tabular data for dynamic applications on mobile devices.

Summer 2013 Undergraduate Research Assistant, HMC Computer Science Department

CLAREMONT, CA Visualizing the Graphical Execution of Abstract Program Traces

Advisor: Ben Wiedermann. Modified the UC Santa Barbara JavaScript Abstract Interpreter to output runtime information about the abstract program trace and implemented a tool for

visualizing program traces using D3.js.

Jane Hoffswell Curriculum Vitae

Summer 2012 Undergraduate Research Assistant, HMC Computer Science Department

CLAREMONT, CA Large Scale, Educational Video Games for Middle School Students

Advisor: Elizabeth Sweedyk. Developed a math-based game for the iPad that teaches children about ratios by taking advantage of the ratio-based behavior of mixing paint.

#### HONORS AND AWARDS

2020 ACM CHI Best Paper Award (for "Techniques for Flexible Responsive Visualization Design")

2019 ACM CHI 2019 Doctoral Consortium Award

Hopper x 1 Seattle 2019 Scholarship Award Recipient

2014 Jeff Dean - Heidi Hopper Endowed Regental Fellowship Recipient

Harvey Mudd College Computer Science Clinic Poster Award

Honorable Mention CRA Undergraduate Research Award Competition

2011-2014 Harvey Mudd College Dean's List

2010 International Baccalaureate Diploma

## **THESIS**

2020 Languages and Visualization Tools for Data-Centric End-User Programming of Interactive Visualizations. **Jane Hoffswell.** Committee: Jeffrey Heer (Advisor), Alan Borning, Amy J. Ko <a href="http://hdl.handle.net/1773/45922">http://hdl.handle.net/1773/45922</a>

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

2020 Techniques for Flexible Responsive Visualization Design.

Jane Hoffswell, Wilmot Li, and Zhicheng Liu.

CHI 2020. doi.org/10.1145/3313831.3376777 [24% Acceptance Rate, Best Paper (Top 1%)]

2019 Interactive Repair of Tables Extracted from PDF Documents on Mobile Devices.

Jane Hoffswell and Zhicheng Liu.

CHI 2019. doi.org/10.1145/3290605.3300523 [24% Acceptance Rate]

2018 SetCoLa: High-Level Constraints for Graph Layout.

Jane Hoffswell, Alan Borning, Jeffrey Heer.

Euro Vis 2018. doi.org/10.1111/cgf.13440 [29% Acceptance Rate]

Augmenting Code with In Situ Visualizations to Aid Program Understanding.

Jane Hoffswell, Arvind Satyanarayan, Jeffrey Heer.

CHI 2018. doi.org/10.1145/3173574.3174106 [26% Acceptance Rate]

Supporting Patient-Provider Collaboration to Identify Individual Triggers using Food and Symptom Journals. Jessica Schroeder, **Jane Hoffswell**, Chia-Fang Chung, James Fogarty, Sean Munson, Jasmine Zia. CSCW 2017. doi.org/10.1145/2998181.2998276 [35% Acceptance Rate]

2016 Visual Debugging Techniques for Reactive Data Visualization.

Jane Hoffswell, Arvind Satyanarayan, Jeffrey Heer.

Euro Vis 2016. doi.org/10.1111/cgf.12903 [27% Acceptance Rate]

Reactive Vega: A Streaming Dataflow Architecture for Declarative Interactive Visualization.

Arvind Satyanarayan, Ryan Russell, **Jane Hoffswell**, Jeffrey Heer.

InfoVis 2016. doi.org/10.1109/TVCG.2015.2467091 [22% Acceptance Rate]

Jane Hoffswell Curriculum Vitae

# WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

Spring 2019 Languages & Visualizations to Enable Effective End User Programming.

GLASGOW, UK Jane Hoffswell.

CHI Extended Abstracts 2019. doi.org/10.1145/3290607.3299067

Spring 2015 Debugging Vega through Inspection of the Data Flow Graph.

Cagliari, Italy Jane Hoffswell, Arvind Satyanarayan, Jeffrey Heer.

Euro Vis Workshop on Reproducibility, Verification, and Validation in Visualization (EuroRV3), 2015.

doi.org/10.2312/eurorv3.20151144

**POSTERS** 

Spring 2019 LANGUAGES & VISUALIZATIONS TO ENABLE EFFECTIVE END USER PROGRAMMING.

GLASGOW, UK ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems Doctoral Consortium Poster, 2019.

Fall 2016 VISUAL DEBUGGING TECHNIQUES FOR REACTIVE DATA VISUALIZATION.

SEATTLE, WA University of Washington Computer Science & Engineering Affiliates, 2016.

LEADERSHIP AND VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

2018 - 2020 GRAD, VGRAD, & POSTDOC ADVISORY COUNCIL, UW COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

SEATTLE, WA Participated as a council member of the G5PAC to discuss and address the needs of

researchers and teaching assistants in the Paul G. Allen School.

Winter 2020 PRACTICE TALKS SEMINAR ORGANIZER (CSE591L), UW COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

Seattle, WA Organized and lead a new weekly seminar focused on presenting and providing feedback

on practice talks from graduate students in the Paul G. Allen School.

2017 - present REVIEWER

ACM CHI - ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems 2017, 2019-2020

IEEE VIS - IEEE Visualization 2018-2020
ACM UIST - ACM User Interface Software and Technology 2017-2020
IEEE TVCG - IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics 2018

Recognition for Outstanding Reviews: CHI 2019

Winter 2018 HCI VISIT DAYS COORDINATOR, UW COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

SEATTLE, WA Organized group activities and one-on-one meetings for admitted graduate students.

Fall 2016 GRADUATE STUDENT ADMISSIONS VOLUNTEER, UW COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

SEATTLE, WA Reviewed graduate student admissions applications.

Fall 2015 New Graduate Orientation Leader, UW Computer Science & Engineering

SEATTLE, WA Coordinated talks from current students and faculty for incoming graduate students,

organized activities for the event, and hosted the two-day orientation.

2013-2014 PROJECT MANAGER, CAPSTONE PROJECT, HMC COMPUTER SCIENCE DEPARTMENT

CLAREMONT, CA Visualizing and Exploring Performance Data alongside VMware

Advisor: Melissα O'Neill. Acted as project manager for a senior capstone project with

VMware in which we developed a dashboard for visualizing system performance using D3.js.

Fall 2015 Project Manager, USLI Rocketry Team, Harvey Mudd College

CLAREMONT, CA Founder and project manager of a NASA sponsored rocketry team for the University

Student Launch Initiative (USLI). Designed and launched a rocket with a scientific payload.

Jane Hoffswell Curriculum Vitae

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2020 - present Lecturer, UW Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science & Engineering SEATTLE, WA CSE442 — Data Visualization (Spring 2017) Co-Instructor: Jeffrey Heer Developed curriculumn, taught lecturers, graded coursework, managed teaching assistants. TEACHING ASSISTANT, UW PAUL G. ALLEN SCHOOL OF COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING 2016-2017 SEATTLE, WA CSE442 — Data Visualization (Spring 2017). Professor: Jeffrey Heer CSE512 — Data Visualization (Spring 2016). Professor: Jeffrey Heer Graded coursework, held office hours, and taught extra tutorial sessions. TEACHING ASSISTANT, UW MASTERS IN HUMAN COMPUTER INTERACTION + DESIGN Winter 2014 SEATTLE, WA HCID520 - User Interface Software & Technology (Wi 2014). Professor: Jeffrey Heer Helped to develop the course curriculum. Tutored and graded coursework. 2012-2014 TUTOR AND GRADER, HMC COMPUTER SCIENCE DEPARTMENT Professor: Melissa O'Neill Claremont, CA CS131 – Programming Languages (Spring 2014). Professor: Jim Boerkoel CS151 - Artificial Intelligence (Spring 2014). CS121 - Software Development (Fall 2013). Professor: Mike Erlinger Professor: Elizabeth Sweedyk CS121 - Software Development (Spring 2013). CS60 - Principles of Computer Science (Fall 2012). Professor: Zach Dodds

#### **TALKS**

Spring 2020
Seattle, WA
DUB Shorts, University of Washington. https://vimeo.com/418215216

Spring 2020
Seattle, WA
UW Allen School Women's Research Day. https://youtu.be/EJtakt7l3BQ

Spring 2014
San Diego, CA
Southern California Celebration for Women in Computing.

Fall 2013
Los Angeles, CA
Summer 2012
Santa Ana, CA
HARVEY MUDD College NASA University Student Launch Initiative Team Presentation.
Alaa Southern California Aerospace Systems and Technology (ASAT) Conference.

# **GRADUATE COURSEWORK**

2019 Research Methods and Data Analysis in Software Systems Research

2017 Accurate Computing · Constraint Programming

Graded coursework and held office hours.

2016 Advanced Topics in HCI · Computer-Aided Reasoning for Software · Research Design

2015 Computer Systems · Data Visualization · Principles of Database Management Systems

2014 Machine Learning

#### RELEVANT SKILLS

Coding: JavaScript, Python, HTML/CSS, D3.js, Vega/Vega-Lite

User Research: Semi-Structured Interviews, Surveys, Experimental Design

Leadership: Project Management, Scientific & Technical Writing, Presentations

Tools: GitHub, Tableau, LaTeX, Keynote, Microsoft Excel, OmniGraffle